So today I’m gonna tell you the best three
stories that I know, I think, and, I think
these stories are absolutely, phenomenally
potent, and the reason for that is that I
think they illustrate in an extraordinarily-powerful
way the nature of the processes that led to
the establishment of western democratic ideals.
Mircae Eliade, whose work I rely on substantially,
to make the following argument, has taken
western academic culture to task in a manner
that hasn’t fully been revealed yet.
He said that, like all human cultures, the
west is parochial and narrow in its viewpoint,
and although over the last three hundred years
there’s been a substantial amount of cross-cultural
intermingling and a potential broadening of
philosophical and religious horizon, that
broadening has not been sufficiently complete;
If we build on the viewpoint that I’ve been
developing with you over the last few courses
and make the presupposition that religious
modes of thinking are more phenomenological
than they are rational, which means that they
deal more with what you experience, say, than
with the objective world, if we look at archaic
religious stories through that lens, then
they can start to open up, and so, given that,
I want to open up three religious stories
to you today, two in depth, and one only in
passing because we’ll return to it later.
I’ll start with, Judeo-Christian Myth of
Genesis, and when I say myth, of course, you
all know this already, but when I say myth,
I don’t mean untruth, I mean a form of knowledge
that’s narrative in structure and predicated
on presumptions that aren’t empirical; a
myth describes processes of transformation,
a myth describes them, a myth describes the
process whereby elements of experience come
into being and transform
On Genesis, the fundamental structural elements
of Genesis are the Word of God and chaos,
and the Hebrew words for chaos and waste are
tehom, for chaos, and tohu, for waste, and
tehom in particular, although toho as well,
are very interesting words because you can
track their derivation historically, and sometimes
if you contract the derivation of words historically,
you can get some sense of the culture milieu
out of which the word sprang,
and we know what tyomat means because we have
written records of a story that involves a
character named Tiamat, and Tiamat is a dragon
who lives at the bottom of the ocean; in the
oldest creation myth we have, which is the
Enuma Elish, the Sumerian creation myth, the
Sumeria, Babylon, Acadia, rightly regarded
as the birthplace of modern western civilization.
In Genesis, two processes unite to produce
being, the first of those processes or states
is chaos, represented by taom or tohu.
The second of those processes is logos, and
logos is another word that has an extraordinarily
broad range of meaning; it’s generally transcribed
in the Christian tradition as the word, and
it’s identified with Christ, which is a
very peculiar identification because it’s
the Word of God that creates order out of
chaos and, of course, the Word of God in Genesis
is a phenomena that predates the birth of
Christ infinitely from a classical religious
perspective, so the fact that the two beings
are identified as of great peculiarity and
also of great interest.
The fundamental story of Genesis is something
like this, and it’s perhaps the most brilliant
contribution of Judeo-Christian thought to
world history, its total impact is virtually
incalculable.
The idea is this: that chaos can be conceptualized
as something that has an essentially feminine
aspect as a matrix, and a matrix is a structure
from which other structures emerge, and the
story in Genesis makes the hypothesis that
logos, which is the Word of God, a phenomena
associated with speech and communication and
logic, logos: logic, rationality, courage,
exploration, all combined into a single entity
or trait: logos, the combination of logos
and chaos is what brings order into being;
that’s what the story in Genesis means;
it’s not an empirical description of the
origin of objects, it’s a phenomenological
description of the origin of experience,
the idea being that without the piercing glance
of whatever consciousness is, whatever the
background of experience is, the matrix, chaos,
cannot be conceptualized as real; it takes
the interplay between the feminine principle,
chaos, and the masculine principle, logos,
in order to produce being.
Now that’s of substantial importance when
you give some consideration to the fact that
immediately in Genesis, after the establishment
of livable order, the deity yahva identifies
the individual human being with logos, right,
made in God’s image, that’s the essential
characteristic of the human being, and what
that means is that the logos that operates
in human beings, which is this capacity to
make order out of chaos, is identical to the
principle that gives rise to the cosmos from
a mythological perspective, so it partakes
of the deity in a very direct sense insofar
as being itself is dependent on its operation.
Now it’s still possible to claim, given
that perspective, that a story with that sort
of structure is superstitious and that it
doesn’t bear any relationship to what reality,
what actually constitutes reality, but you
have to understand that that story, old as
it is, is predicated on older stories, and
it’s on the ground that those older stories
establish that our entire concept of natural
rights rests, so if you believe that natural
rights have an existence more than merely
arbitrary, the reason you believe that is
because they’re predicated, those rights
are predicated on the ideas that are expressed
in these myths,
Okay, so now we’re gonna go back in time
to Sumeria, and I’m gonna show you how the
Sumerian creation myth lays itself out, and
not only that, I’m going to describe to
you the direct political implications of the
Enuma Elish, the Sumerian creation myth, because
the political implications of that myth are
well understood because the political structure
of Sumeria was directly associated with the
structure of the myth because the Sumeria
was regarded as the earthly represent of the
highest God in the Mesopotamian Pantheon,
whose name was Marduk, so insofar as you were
emperor, the reason that you were emperor,
and the, this is what gave your sovereignty
legitimacy, right, ‘cause sovereignty has
to have legitimacy otherwise there’s constant
revolutions.
What gave sovereignty legitimacy in Mesopotamia
was the identification of the emperor with
Marduk, and that had, that had certain implications
for the emperor, which we’ll discuss in
some detail
So the story starts like this.
You’ve got this Dragon, Tiamat, and Tiamat
is a great primordial beast, who lives at
the bottom of the ocean.
And the ocean is water and water is associated
with the primal element in archaic thinking
and I told you, there’s reasons for that
already.
or if you viewed the transformation of deserts
as a consequence of rain, you can understand
why water would be considered the element
that gives life, right, that the element that,
that brings life forth, and we know from an
evolutionary perspective that that’s accurate.
And we know that we’re 90 per cent water
and so to consider water the primal element
is no trivial conclusion.
No, no less than presuming that the sun is
the ultimate source of light, the ultimate
god, because the sun is the ultimate source
of life as far as earth, as far as we’re
concerned on earth, right, because it’s
the source of all our energy.
These aren’t stupid concepts, all right.
So Tiamat is this horrible creature that lurks
at the bottom of the primal element, all right.
Now she has a husband, Apsu.
Now the Mesopotamian creation myth doesn’t
say much about Apsu.
We only know that he’s the male consort
of the Dragon of Chaos.
And we know from reading other sources of
mythology that the male consort of the Dragon
of Chaos generally represents either logos
or culture.
So we’re gonna make the presupposition in
this particular case that the husband of Chaos
is Order or Culture, okay, and then the Mesopotamians
don’t say much about that, that doesn’t,
the development of the idea of Apsu or Order
or Culture, doesn’t take new force until
the ancient Egyptians and we’ll talk about
them today too.
Okay so Tiamat and Apsu are locked into a
kind of sexual embrace according to the Mesopotamian
creation.
What does that mean?
It kinda means two things.
It means that they’re not really distinguishable
because they’re locked into this embrace
and it also means that they’re up to something
creative because the act of sexual congress
in mythology is most usefully, is most frequently
utilized as representation of something creative
or as representation of the probability of
some new form coming to be, right.
All right.
So Apsu and Tiamat are locked into this embrace
in a state that other creation myths describe
as egg-like, the Pre-Cosmogonic egg, their
intermingling gives rise to the initial state
of being according to the Sumerians and the
initial state of being according to the Sumerians
is characterized by the dominion of the elder
gods
These gods, being none too bright, make a
tremendous amount of racket, doing things.
Well what does that mean exactly?
Well it means something like this.
They make a lot of racket and they cause a
lot of trouble.
They make a lot of wind and all of their racket
and trouble and wind and activity rouses Tiamat.
What does that mean?
Well it means if you do things, you get in
trouble.
It means even if you’re trying to solve
problems, you get into trouble because the
solution to a problem tend, tends to generate
a whole bunch of new problems, right.
It’s like the Hydra.
So what it means is that it’s more or less
fated that any form of activity whatsoever
is likely to produce the threat of catastrophe
And of course we’re absolutely keenly aware
of that in the modern world because we’re
possessed by this sense that all of our frenetic
activity, all of our frenetic motivated activity
is producing alterations in the world order
such that Nature itself is going to
be destroyed and eliminate us, right.
That’s classic Sumerian fear.
Nothing’s changed in the last 5,000 years.
The Sumerians presumed that once the elder
gods where constructed and started moving
around on the planet, that their activity
their mindless activity, because remember
these aren’t well integrated motivational
forces, they’re more like primordial beasts,
right.
Their unintegrated activity risks plunging
everything back in Chaos.
Well Tiamat’s the representative of Chaos,
this generative Chaos, but so what if the
Sumerians say, “Well the elder gods cause
a lot of racket, they move around the planet
and they upset Tiamat,” and she decides
that enough is enough and she’s gonna wipe
them out.
So she’s sitting at the bottom of the ocean,
fuming away, as the elder gods go about their
business and then they take one step too many
and they kill Apsu, who’s her husband.
Now the Sumerian creation myth doesn’t say
much about this, but we know that Apsu is
the male consort of Chaos.
That makes him Order.
So what happens is the elder gods destroy
Order itself.
They destroy Culture itself and as soon as
you destroy Culture, all hell breaks loose
and that’s exactly what happens in this
Sumerian creation myth.
So Tiamat emerges, he’s gonna wipe everything
out and the world will revert back to its
primordial, non-existent state.
Now the, all the gods get wind of this and
of course they’re just terrified because
they know that this thing that gave rise to
them, whatever it is, the matrix of being,
can easily wipe them out at a moment’s notice
and so despite the fact that they are transpersonal
and immortal and characterized by a certain
amount of power, in the face of absolute Chaos,
they’re insufficient.
Now this occurrence is extending over a protracted
period of time and as the elder gods are threatened,
they’re also breeding and mating and producing
new forms.
And they produce a great, great grandson,
whose name is Marduk.
Now Marduk has a lot of very interesting attributes.
So the attributes are described in the Enuma
Elish in the following manner, so this is
what Marduk’s father sees when his wife,
Damkina, gives birth to Marduk.
“So when he, who’s Marduk’s father,
saw his son, he rejoiced, he beamed, his heart
was filled with joy.
He distinguished him and conferred upon him
double equality with the gods.”
Okay, so that’s that first indication that
whatever Marduk represents is something that’s
elevated beyond the normal status of a primordial
deity.
“So that he was highly exalted and surpassed
them in everything.
Artfully arranged beyond comprehension were
his members, not fit for human understanding,
hard to look upon, four were his eyes, four
were his ears.
When his lips moved, fired blazed forth.
Each of his four ears grew large and likewise,
his eyes, to see everything.
He was exalted among gods.
Surpassing was his form.
His members were gigantic.
He was surpassing in height.
Mariyutu, Mariyutu.”
One of his names.
“Sun of the sun god, the sun god of the
gods.”
Okay.
Complex bit of poetry.
Says a bunch of things.
It says well whatever Marduk is, is the offspring
of the gods.
Whatever Marduk is, is characterized by heightened
awareness.
Right?
Because he has four ears and they’re large.
Whatever Marduk is characterized by is the
status that surpasses that of his fathers.
Whatever he’s characterized by, is associated
with the power of speech, real power, because
when he speaks, fire spurts forth.
Marduk is also huge, but more importantly,
he’s associated in this particular poem
with the sun.
Why is that?
Well the sun dominates consciousness, right,
because we’re conscious during the day.
Most of our brain is visual cortex, so we’re
visual creatures.
So when the sun rises is when the day begins.
So Marduk is also associated with whatever
deity dominates the day and that’s the deity
of consciousness.
And there’s more to the story of the Sun,
right, because the Sun is also something that
rises and sets repeatedly and that means that
the deity that dominates consciousness is
characterized by a cyclical nature.
That’s a Sun myth.
Sun rises in the morning renewed, as a consequence
of fighting a terrible battle in the night
with the enemies of everything that’s associated
with consciousness.
A classic solar myth
So Apsu and Tiamat give rise to the world
of the gods.
The activity of the world of gods reawakens
Tiamat, she decides to destroy everything,
but at that moment the gods give birth to
Marduk.
Now that’s a typical motif which is that
the hero’s always born at the time of maximal
crisis and the reason for that is in part,
it’s simple.
Look, if your culture is dealing well with
the forces of the unknown, so that everything
is static, but, static but productive, so
that problems themselves don’t arise, there’s
no reason for the hero, right, there’s no
reason to confront the unknown.
It’s only when crisis beckons that the birth
of the hero is necessary.
Marduk constitutes the birth of the hero.
and they say, “Look, you know, we’re in
real trouble unless someone goes out there
and confronts Tiamat straight on, she’s
gonna wipe everything out, it’s a dangerous
and terrifying job, but somebody has to do
it.
And Marduk says, “Oh that’s no problem
but I got a few rules here and this is the
first rule, I’m in charge from here on forward.”
What does that mean exactly?
Well these archaic stories are polysemus and,
or polysemic in Northrup Frye’s terminology
and what that means is that they can be read
validly at multiple levels of analysis simultaneously.
And so one thing it means is that if you take
the 2-year-old child who’s essentially under
the Dominion of assorted primordial gods and
goddesses.
Right?
Aggression, fear, panic, and according to
Freud, a certain degree of sexual aggression.
The child moves from motivated state to domination
for motivated state It isn’t until the age
of 3 and 4 when, under the pressure applied
by the social world and as a consequence of
the maturation of the prefrontal cortex, which
matures throughout childhood and adolescence
and doesn’t reach its final form until perhaps
into the early 20s, all of those fundamental
motivational forces start taking on a structured
relationship to one another, which is to say
that once your, as your personality becomes
integrated, a single motive force forward
has to bring all of these underlying motivational
systems into some sort of harmonious arrangement.
Okay so let’s, let’s see what the Sumerians
are doing here.
Okay, first of all they’re, they’re doing
psychology.
They’re trying to figure out, given the
dominion of the, the elder gods, the indisputable
dominion of the elder gods, Instincts, who
should rule?
Right?
What should be in charge?
How do you construct a hierarchy of values?
And then more complexly, when you integrate
a state, which is what the Mesopotamians did,
right, the first great civilization, what
does that mean?
The first time hundreds of tribes were hammered
into some sort of stable, hierarchical order,
how do you represent that order?
“So Marduk gets his act together, the gods
all meet in a huge chamber, they elect him
king and then they prepare him for battle.
When the gods, the fathers, beheld the power
of his word, they were glad and did homage,
saying ‘Marduk is king’.
They bestowed upon him a scepter, a throne
and a royal robe.
They gave him an irresistable weapon, smiting
the enemy saying, ‘Go and cut off the life
of Tiamat.
May the winds carry her blood to out-of-the-way
places.’
After the gods, his fathers, had determined
the destiny of Marduk, they set him on the
road, the way to success and attainment.”
So then he goes to the “heart of darkness”
so to speak and confronts Tiamat, accuses
her of treachery and challenges her to battle.
“When Tiamat heard this, she became like
one in a frenzy and lost her reason.
She cried out loud and furiously.
To the very roots, her two legs shook back
and forth.
She recited an incantation, repeatedly casting
her spell.
As for the gods of battle, they sharpened
their weapons.
Tiamat and Marduk, the wisest of the gods,
advanced against one another.
They pressed on into combat and approached
for battle.”
Okay, well things don’t go out so well with
Tiamat from this point forward.
The first thing that Marduk does is encapsulate
her in a net and I think that’s a really
interesting metaphor because that’s essentially
what human beings do when they encounter the
unknown, right.
They encapsulate it in an explanatory network,
so it’s a way of binding up the, the anomaly,
or the unknown, and giving it a substantive
form.
“Then he cuts her into pieces and then he
makes the world out of her pieces.
In fact one of Marduk’s names is ‘He Who
Makes Ingenious Things’ as a consequence
of the combat with Tiamat.”
Now that’s very, very interesting because
what it means is that the Sumerians are presenting
in metaphorical form the notion that when
the chips are down, the survival of being
depends on the capacity of whatever Marduk
represents, the solar god, to encounter the
matrix of being, to cut it into pieces and
to make the world and if you think about in
those terms, it’s a very, very straightforward
story, right.
It’s basically the story of human beings,
fundamentally the story of human beings, because
we, in the words of a famous evolutionary
psychologist, whose name completely escapes
me, we occupy the cognitive niche, right.
Our mode of being is creativity in the face
of the unknown and when Chaos threatens the
established mode of being, it’s necessary
for us to put our creativity into action and
to carve out new territory as a consequence
of encounter with the unknown.
Why?
Well because we can take the world apart with
our hands and put it together in new ways
and then we can code what we’ve done verbally
and we can transmit it to another person and
then they can do the same thing.
And we’re all doing this all the time and
we’re all telling each other how we’re
doing it.
And that’s how the embodiment of logos in
the human being, which is precisely equivalent
to the Sumerian notion of Marduk, that’s
precisely how it is that we’re constantly
capable of redeeming the world.
and that’s why you make resolutions at New
Year’s because the new you is supposed to
be born at the new year.
OK, so what do the
Mesopotamians do at the new year?
They take their king and they bring him outside
the city.
Now you have to understand that outside the
city is chaos, right, because these are city
states.
When you go outside the dominion of the human,
you’re in chaos.
And then the priest makes the emperor kneel
and takes all his marks of status off him
so he’s reduced to his essence fundamentally,
bereft of his social persona, and then he
slaps him with a glove and humiliateshim and
the king is forced to recount his sins, right,
everything he did in the
last year that wasn’t up to Marduk standards,
so to speak.
And you can see, that’d be a pretty useful
thing to have somebody who’s in power do
on a regular basis, right, because it reminds
them that they’re in fact subject to a trans-personal
structure whose nature isn’t precisely evident
but is nonetheless there, which is the case.
Act like Marduk or all hell will break loose
and demolish your kingdom, which of course
is true now,
as it was then now.
So the emperor gets humiliated, he has to
recount his sins, then he’s locked up, then
he
Re-enacts the battle with Tiamat and when
he emerges victorious, he’s locked up with
a ritual prostitute, a hierodule, and they
mate.
Why?
Well, the
Hierodule, the ritual prostitute, represents
Tiamat.
Now why the hell
would that be, because Tiamat’s a dragon,
right, a horrible man-eating dragon that lives
at the bottom of the ocean which is to say
that in any encounter with the
unknown, as difficult traumatic and violent
as that might be, there’s also the possibility
for something creative to emerge as a consequence,
right, because it’s out of the
unknown that we mine new information
So insofar as the Mesopotamian emperor acted
out the role of Marduk, then he was a good
emperor, then he deserved his sovereignty
and literally as well as figuratively, insofar
as he did play that role, then the society
was going to remain not only stable but constantly
updated because he’s engaged in this constant
creative contact with the unknown, aided and
abetted by his attempts to remember his own
inadequacies and weaknesses and to do something
about them.
OK, so that’s a pretty interesting story
and it gets even more interesting when you
start to understand that the Judao-Christian
myth is assimilated to the Sumerian creation
myth by the union of the notions of chaos
and Tiamat.
So the logos in Judao-Christian thinking,
the word of God that produces order out of
chaos, is also essentially equivalent – at
least metaphorically speaking – to whatever
Marduk represents in the Sumerian creation
myth.
And we know that I mean our relationship with
the Enuma Elish is obscured by time but our
relationship with the stories that lay out
the fundamental sub-structure of western culture
is not so ameliorated even though we may not
believe them explicitly anymore.
They still sit at the basis of our society.